Henry Wadsworth Longfellow Collection
Henry Wadsworth Longfellow Collection
1852-1888
Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882
24 items (SC)
Correspondence, manuscripts, miscellanea of the American poet.
2607308
Biographical History
Henry Wadsworth Longfellow (1807-1882) was an American poet whose works include "Paul Revere's Ride", The Song of Hiawatha, and "Evangeline". He was also the first American to translate Dante Alighieri's The Divine Comedy. He studied at Bowdoin College and later became a professor there; he also taught at Harvard.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Henry Wadsworth Longfellow Collection constitutes five letters and two autograph poems by the American author and poet, as well as a small assortment of miscellany relating to Longfellow, his children, and one of his correspondents.
Arrangement of the Collection
Letters are arranged chronologically. Miscellany is arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882 -- Archives; Arrow and the song.; Psalm of life.; Poets, American -- 19th century.; Correspondence.; Photographs.; Negatives (photographs); Business cards.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John S. Mayfield; Sol Feinstone.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Fred B. Page, M.D. ("My Dear Doctor," with parodies of Longfellow poems), 1852, Dec 9 (Sc 138)
  - "My Dear Mr Street", 1865, Nov. 16 (Sc 138)
  - Charles Cottnam Hamilton ("My Dear Sir"), 1871, Nov. 21 (Sc 138)
  - William Dean Howells ("Dear Mr Howells"), 1872, Mar 14? (Sc 138)
  - Charles Cottnam Hamilton ("My Dear Sir"), 1877, Apr 26 (Sc 138)
- Manuscripts
  - "The Arrow and the Song", undated (Sc 138)
  - "A Psalm of Life" (last verse); gift of Sol Feinstone, 6 Apr 1881 (Sc 138)
- Miscellany
  - Autograph of Henry Wadsworth Longfellow (Sc 138)
  - Business card: Mr. H. W. Longfellow (Sc 138)
  - Cartes de visite
    - Longfellow's children (Sc 138)
    - Evangeline, 2 items (Sc 138)
  - Engravings, 2 items (Sc 138)
  - Letter ( undated) to Amy Bridgeman and receipt ( 1888 Oct 10) to Mary Bridgeman of Alice M. Longfellow (Sc 138)
  - Photographic prints (4) and negative (1) of Charles Cottnam Hamilton (1813-1880), recipient of two of the letters, above, 5 items (Sc 138)